-
Speaker 1: Thanks so much, Mr.
Chairman. Curious about the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): title of this hearing. The title of the hearing is Abortion Bans and Interstate Travel for Care After Dobbs.
This seems
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): like an attempt to mislead, seriously mislead the American people into thinking that one or more states
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): are out there criminalizing or otherwise utilizing the coercive force of the state to prohibit travel to obtain an abortion in another state. I'm not aware of a single state that's doing that, not one. I'm not aware of a single state that's planning to do it. Now,
the only
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): thing I
Speaker 3: can think of that it could relate to is minors, the transportation of minors, underage children.
across
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): state lines in order to get an abortion, which leads me to wonder whether this is really just about the pro-abortion activist community and lobby wanting to allow traffickers and abusers and abortion providers to transport children across state lines without their parents' knowledge or consent
in order to
Speaker 4: get an abortion.
It's a
Speaker 3: violation of basic standards of decency. It's
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): a violation of
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): parental rights in order to do this. This is not what the title of the hearing seems to suggest, which is that states are out there criminalizing interstate travel by a woman who wants to get an abortion in another state. Not one state is doing that. Not one state is considering legislation to do that. Now, don't just take my word for it on this, on what this is really
about.
that is the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): interstate transportation of minors, of children, without their parents' knowledge or consent so they can get an abortion. Planned Parenthood employees have themselves confirmed it. An adult male working undercover as an investigator with Project Veritas in Missouri told Planned Parenthood employees that he was seeking an abortion for a 13-year-old girl without her parents' knowledge or
consent.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): According to court filings, after acknowledging that the abortion would be illegal in that circumstance in Missouri, the Planned Parenthood employees offered to help transport this 13-year-old girl to another Planned Parenthood in Kansas, assuring the man that the parents would not find out. They would never know. The managing director said, quote,
we never
Speaker 3: tell parents anything. She's an adult.
in our
Speaker 3: clinics, close quote.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): She's 13.
When the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): reporter asked how to transport the 13-year-old girl to
Kansas for an
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): abortion, the managing director said that this was, quote, not their first rodeo. They're gonna know exactly how to handle that, close quote. The managing director went so far as to write a doctor's note to the child's school saying, quote, we can cut off our letterhead so it doesn't even say where the child's
going.
and
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): offered to arrange transportation for the child, get the child to Kansas and even pay for the abortion, lodging
and other
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): services so that the 13 year old girl could undergo an abortion, a significant surgical medical procedure, one that in some circumstances can present complications
Speaker 5: that themselves can be life-threatening, all without her parents' knowledge or consent.
This
Speaker 5: is appalling. Dr. Scupp,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): do you believe it's ethical to conduct an elective, non-emergency, surgical procedure of any kind, on a minor, on a child, without notifying and obtaining the consent of the parents and in fact actively concealing the fact from the parents that the procedure is happening?
- No,
Speaker 6: it's a bedrock standard of medical care that we do not commit a procedure of any type. Upon a minor, they are not felt to be able to give informed consent by themselves, and we do need the parents' consent.
Speaker 7: - Okay. Now,
Speaker 5: how dangerous, so it's not just any adult that needs to consent, it needs to be the parent, unless parental rights have been terminated or something like that, right?
Speaker 8: - Yeah, if there's a legal guardian. - Right.
Speaker 5: Now, how dangerous is it to conceal a surgical
Speaker 5: procedure perhaps an abortion for example from
Speaker 9: parents the parents of a teenage girl who might experience complications from
the abortion
Speaker 10: in this particular instance every person I believe in this room would want to know if
Speaker 6: their child was in that sort of a circumstance and and be able to come alongside their child to provide support this child needs mental health care we don't know who the abuser is is it someone in that family does this This child need to be removed from that family.
Speaker 6: toward child protective services, to law enforcement. As a civil society, we should want whoever impregnated that girl, which is by definition statutory rape, to be prosecuted. We should want to stop this from ever occurring. The abortion will not fix the girl. It will not restore her innocence. It will merely add trauma to trauma.
Speaker 6: And, we know that mental health complications are quite frequent, particularly in this sort
of a situation. And
Speaker 11: particularly if her parents don't know what happened and she experiences
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): complications, that could be a problem. I was shocked to read the story that you linked in your testimony of an Idaho woman and her adult son who were charged with kidnapping his 15-year-old girlfriend when they forced her to travel to Oregon for an abortion without her parents' permission.
The
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): son has also been charged with rape of a minor and producing sexually explicit material involving a minor. Are these the type of people who some at this hearing want to protect with their opposition to parental notification
laws?
We hear
Speaker 6: so much discussion about this heartbreaking situation, and yet in the same, when we turn the page and see that there are those who are willing to facilitate the transport of these minors without their parents, we recognize that that's being used as
a
Speaker 12: tool, that there's really very little care for that child in that tragic situation. Mr.
Speaker 13: Chairman, I've got one small follow-up question, if I could ask one more. Sure. Go ahead. Thank you.
Of course.
Tell
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): me what the Supreme Court held in Troxell v. Granville regarding parental rights and how that might apply here to the transportation of a minor to another state without the parent's knowledge or consent for the child to undergo a major surgical procedure, one that in many
Speaker 14: circumstances can carry substantial risks for the child's health. It seems clear that that's not permissible under the relevant
Speaker 15: precedent. And why is it not permissible? What is it that we know about parental rights from Troxell?
Speaker 16: Parental rights are sacrosanct and essential, and they're essential bedrock principle of the rights that citizens of the United States, people in the United States enjoy.
Thank
Speaker 4: you.